<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certaine short prayers and meditations vpon the Lords prayer and the Ten commandements With other particular prayers for seuerall purposes. Written by the right worshipfull Sir Iames Perrott Knight.</title>
            <title>Certaine short prayers and meditations upon the Lords prayer and the Ten commandments.</title>
            <author>Perrott, James, Sir, 1571-1637.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 119 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09489</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19772</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106420</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842136</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842136</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6766</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09489)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6766)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 585:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certaine short prayers and meditations vpon the Lords prayer and the Ten commandements With other particular prayers for seuerall purposes. Written by the right worshipfull Sir Iames Perrott Knight.</title>
                  <title>Certaine short prayers and meditations upon the Lords prayer and the Ten commandments.</title>
                  <author>Perrott, James, Sir, 1571-1637.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 207 [i.e. 211], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Aug. Mathewes for Robert Svvayne, and are to be sold at the signe of the Bible, at Britaines Burse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Meditations vpon the Lords prayer.</note>
                  <note>With a final colophon leaf.</note>
                  <note>Page 211 misnumbered 207.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayer-books --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6766:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6766:1"/>
            <p>CERTAINE Short PRAYERS and MEDITATIONS vpon the Lords Prayer and the Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements.</p>
            <p>With other parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Prayers for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall purpoſes.</p>
            <p>Written by the right Worſhipfull Sir <hi>IAMES PERROTT</hi> Knight.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Aug. Mathewes</hi> for ROBERT SVVAYNE, and are to be ſold at the Signe of the <hi>Bible,</hi> at <hi>Britaines Burſe.</hi> 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6766:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6766:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honorable, WILLIAM Earle of <hi>Pembrooke,</hi> Lord high Steward of his Maieſties Houſhold, one of the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Order of the Garter, and of his Majeſties Honourable Priuy Councell, Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of the Vn uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of <hi>Oxen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT may ſeeme ſtrange vnto
<pb facs="tcp:6766:3"/>ſome, that J be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no profeſſed Diuine; ſhould preſume to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto the viewe and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict of curious Cenſurers, a Treatiſe of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; It being a ſubiect fitteſt for deepe grounded Divines to deale
<pb facs="tcp:6766:3"/>withall. And aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that J ſhould Dedicate theſe my Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ations vnto your Lordſhip. For the firſt, my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe is, that I offer them not for inſtruction of the iudicious, but for the vſe of them that are as
<pb facs="tcp:6766:4"/>weake in Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as I am, and to others of meaner capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, if any ſuch there bee. For my addreſſe of them to your Honour, J haue no other excuſe, or defence, but that which is beſt knowne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:6766:4"/>your Honor, to whom I am more obliged, then my weake Abilities can giue hopes to yeelde other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence, then by Prayer vnto God, that your proceedings may proſper by pietie, and be rewarded
<pb facs="tcp:6766:5"/>with eternall fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt bounden to be at command'ment. IAMES PERROT.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:6766:5"/>
            <head>The Preface to <hi>the inſuing Praiers and Meditations</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Reader may eaſily finde the Writers weakeneſſe: yet in reading per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance he may finde ſowmewhat, though it be but ſimple, that may informe his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and ſtirre vp his minde to better
<pb facs="tcp:6766:6"/>meditations. By vſing that is good, our incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations grow to grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter goodnes; as by the bad, that that which is euil becoms worſe. In this ſmall and ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Tract of mine, of Prayers on the Lords Prayer, and on the Decalogue, or Tenne Commandements.</p>
            <p>The firſt containing the rule of all our Prayers, deliuered by our Lord and Sauiour, who taught vs how, to whom, and for what to pray. This Doctrine being the
<pb facs="tcp:6766:6"/>fountaine, and ſo from it, by vs, there may flow ſtremes of pious Prayers, though our ceſternes are but ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, yet the conduit, or rather Conductor of them, may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by water the fields of our ſoules, and hearts with piety, felicitie, &amp; fertilneſſe, that ſo our ſelues and our poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities may receiue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of all ſpirituall &amp; temporal bleſſings. The true practiſe of Prayer, is as the Path<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to heauen, the guide of our life on
<pb facs="tcp:6766:7"/>earth, the remoouers of ſuch Remoras, and rubbs as doe hinder vs here, and doe ſtay vs from eternall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe hereafter: For our true beliefe, <hi>cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendorum,</hi> of things to bee beleeued, which we call the Creede, is <hi>Regula</hi> &amp; <hi>via vitae,</hi> the rule and way of life. So the Decalogue, or ten Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, being <hi>regula faciendo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> the rule of things to be done, is <hi>vita viae</hi> the life of this way. both theſe making vp by feruent, frequent
<pb facs="tcp:6766:7"/>and faithfull prayers, our progreſſion vnto eternall life. This as a gate, the other as goles vnto eternall glory; betwixt theſe two, Prayers are as the Sayles, &amp; the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit as the wings that carries vs thorow the trobleſome waues of this world, and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vs vp in all tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, afflictions, and calamities. In the vſe of Prayers, as of the other parts of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Humility is the ground, Faith the foundation, Petition
<pb facs="tcp:6766:8"/>and thankeſgiuing the walles, eleuated Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations the roofe, &amp; knowledge ioyned with conſcience, the props and pillars. So is holy prayer made <hi>ſcala caeli,</hi> the ladder that leades vs to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend vnto heauen. Prayer then being the precious balme of <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead,</hi> that cures the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring ſores of our ſinnes; I craue pardon to publiſh theſe my weake conceptions of Prayers and meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; Which procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from no other
<pb facs="tcp:6766:8"/>purpoſe, but to helpe the weake and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, in their well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed devotions. To ſuch I ſay, it is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to pray much, long and often, except it bee done with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generat, a deuout, and an vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding hart, although the ſaying was ancient: <hi>Breuis o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio penetrat caelum;</hi> ſhort Praier pierceth the heauens. Yet it is neither the length, nor ſhortnes of our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that mooues God vnto mercy, vnleſſe they be ioyned with
<pb facs="tcp:6766:9"/>a godly and conſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable vſe of them, in clenſing and caſting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way our corruptions, diſtractions, dulneſſe, coldneſſe, carnal cares &amp; vaine imaginations, which preſſe vpon vs in the time of Prayer, when it is not the voyce, or the ſound of words, but the holy affection and pure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of the heart, with the aſſiſtance of Gods holy ſpirit, that makes our prayers vnto God profitable, and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as the olde verſe hath it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6766:9"/>
            <q>
               <l>Non vox, ſed votum; non cordula muſica, ſed cor:</l>
               <l>Non clamans, ſed amans, cantat in ore Dei.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Which ſignifieth thus much,
<q>
                  <l>Not voyce, but vowes; not muſick but the heart,</l>
                  <l>Not cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es but loue; ſweet ſongs to God impart.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>If any man queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, why ſo many trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes of prayer being publiſhed; my ſelfe or any other ſhould ſet foorth any more; therein yet I conceiue it is with the readers, and ſpecially with the vſers and learners of Prayers, as with Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians
<pb facs="tcp:6766:10"/>who ſeeking ſimples to cure their Patients, goe not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to one garden, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, or fielde to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them, but vnto many: for in ſome places there grows of one kind, in ſome an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other ſort. So in the reliſh, vſe, &amp; choiſe of prayers, which is that herbe of grace; Some deſire ſuch as are ſhort and pithy, others make vſe of them that are of good length &amp; waight. Beſides, this conſideration, though I acknowledge there
<pb facs="tcp:6766:10"/>are diuers excellent treatiſes of Prayers, yet I haue ſeldome ſeene any, that haue cloſly and punctually handled the Petitions of the Lords Prayer, and the parts of the Ten Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, with a ſtrict mixture of Doctrinall Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations in the forme, and to be vſed as prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, containing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their contents, which I haue indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured to doe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my weake skill and iudgement. Firſt, for mine owne
<pb facs="tcp:6766:11"/>exerciſe, and then for the uſe of ſuch as ſhal neede, and deſire it as much as I doe. Which I haue done the rather, becauſe I ſee how feareful, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, and common a thing it is, to finde ſuch multitudes of people, who vſing on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Lords Prayer, or reading the Tenne Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, with out premeditation or knowledge what ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them contains, do yot think that they haue ſufficiently ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued God, when they
<pb facs="tcp:6766:11"/>know little, or vſe not that aright they ſhold know, and doe better. To knowe much and doe little, doth little auaile in diuine or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane things: to doe much &amp; to know little proues vnprofitable, if not hurtfull. Yet not to finde fault with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but to come home vnto my ſelfe: for theſe my Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſuch as they are I leaue them with the readers and vſers of them, to the direction of Gods holy Spirit.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:6766:12"/>
            <head>The Contents of the Prayers and Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons contained in this Booke.</head>
            <p>SEuerall Prayers vpon the ſeuerall Petitions of the Lords Prayer. <hi>1</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One intire Prayer fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med on all the Lords prayer <hi>45</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seuerall Prayers on the Decalogue or Tenne Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements. <hi>57</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Short Meditations for a Chriſtian man to make for the examination of himſelfe, his conſcience, &amp; courſe of life. <hi>112</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6766:12"/>
            <p>A Prayer for the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of thoſe points. <hi>119</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The differences in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion and exerciſes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion betwixt the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants and Koman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques. <hi>124</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Prayer for the peace and proſperity of the Kings Maieſtie, his dominions, and ſubiects. <hi>142</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Prayer for our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted Brethron the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants beyond the Seas <hi>149</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Prayer to be vſed on the Sabbath day. <hi>156</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Prayer in the time of trouble and affliction, <hi>160</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Prayer when publike calamities appr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>, or are doubted. <hi>164</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Prayer againſt the raigning ſinnes, that a man
<pb facs="tcp:6766:13"/>findes to remaine in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. <hi>174</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Prayer neceſſary to be vſed often. <hi>179</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Prayer againſt pride, anger, and Enuy. <hi>193</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Prayer after deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from ſickenes, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of death. <hi>203</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Prayer for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of Zeale.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6766:13"/>
            <head>Certaine ſhort Prayers and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations vpon the Lords Prayer.</head>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>Our Father which art in Heauen, Hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed be thy Name:</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord God, moſt high &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hou art our Father by cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6766:14"/>Wee are thy Children by Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. What an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and happineſſe is it to vs miſerable Men: that thou our mighty God, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafeſt to accept and call vs thy Children: Hauing Elected vs, thou haſt giuen vs a great, a glorious, and an euerlaſting Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Hauing created vs of nothing, thou haſt yet made v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Heires, yea Poſſeſſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of thore then earthly euen heauenly endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Our earthly
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6766:14"/>mould, and our carth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mindes only, keepe vs from this heauenly poſſeſſion. Thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull and powerfull prouidence hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided it; our finne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture keepes vs from it. Thou <hi>(O gracious Father)</hi> haſt giuen vs the earth, and al things in this world to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne; that we might make vſe of it for thy ſeruice, and for our owne ſuſtenance. But the louing of this earth, and the longing after earthly things,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6766:15"/>keepes vs from aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and attaining to thy heauenly Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. If as ſonnes heere on earth, wee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> could ſeeke the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of thee <hi>our Father<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in heauen;</hi> wee ſhould ſooner and bette<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obteine the bleſſings both of Earth and Heauen. If we the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> could conſider where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou haſt choſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vs for thy children and ſo ſhew our ſelue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obedient children i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> keeping thy heauonl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Commandement w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould not only find
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6766:15"/>comfort in our owne ſoules and conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſhunne thy wrath and the ſhipwrake of our ſoules, enioy thy bleſſings, and avoide thy curſes, but bee made partakers of that patrimony, which thou haſt prouided for thine elect chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. But alas (<hi>moſt gracious Father</hi>) wee make our ſelues by our dayly and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall ſinnes vnworthy to be called thy ſons, and moſt vnworthy to receiue the inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of thy children. Yet
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6766:16"/>thou haſt ſent thy only begotten Sonne to ſuffer death for our ſinnes, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore vs thy adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Sonnes to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance which wee by our fallings and tranſgreſſions had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited; yea, to a farre more excellent, and heauenly inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. And yet, as diſobedient children, wee haue againe and againe reuolted from thee, as Prodigall Sonnes miſ-ſpent that Patrimony thou haſt giuen vs, waſted
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6766:16"/>in luxury and luſt, haue beene forced to feede on huskes after wee haue followed ſinne and Satan. And that which is worſe, by our long and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durated ſinnes, wee doe as much as in vs lyeth, crucifie the Lord of life, our el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Brother, thy beſt beloued Son, whom thou haſt ſent, and we haue ſold him by our miſ-beliefes and euill-liuing. As <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> ſold him to the Iewes for a fewe Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents or pieces of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6766:17"/>Thus wee of Children become Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, and of Freeborne made our ſelus ſlaues. Yet (moſt mercifull Father) fince by thy owne choiſethou haſt called vs to bee thy Children, Haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion vpon thy weake, fraile, and wandring Children; bring vs backe from the by-pathes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee haue gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray. Reſtore vs to innocency and to thy fauour. Renewe in vs right ſpirits, Mollifie our ſtony
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6766:17"/>hearts, and giue vs fleſhy hearts. Set thy feare before our eyes, ſo wee ſhall by thy ſtrength honour thee <hi>Our Father which art in Heauen.</hi> So wee by thy helpe ſhall hallow and honour thy hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and euer ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Name. Let vs not diſhonour thee by curſing, ſwearing, or blaſphemy. Thy Name is, as thou art, great and glorious; It is holy as thou art. We cannot hallow it, except thou make vs holy, who of our
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6766:18"/>ſelues are moſt vnho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. O ſanctifie vs thy Children, that wee may hallow thee our Father vpon earth, and in heauen, with Halleluiahs, praiſe, and glory, for euer &amp; euer <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:6766:18"/>
               <head>Thy Kingdome come.</head>
               <p>THy kingdome (O Lord) is an euerlaſting Kingdome, and thy Dominion endureth throughout all ages. The earth is thy foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole, thou fitteſt in the higheſt Heauen, and the Scepter of thy power ſtretcheth ouer all the earth. All things with thee are
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6766:19"/>preſent, as well that is paſt, as that is to come. And yet wee poore ſinners, who ſtand ſtill in thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, doe not as wee ſhould, ſeeke thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: that it ſhould come vnto vs, or that wee by Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance ſhould come vnto thee, that wee might inioy thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. We ſeeke not thy kingdome in thy word to doe thy will: we ſeeke it not in thy workes, to glorifie thee, our Lord &amp; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker. Thou excelleſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6766:19"/>in eminence, whereby thy kingdome in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned. Yet the kings of the earth conſpire againſt thee and thine Anoynted. O make them yet to feele thy high and heauy hand, that they may ſeeke thee, and ſhun the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of thy truth, Church and people, which is a great part of thy kingdom here on earth. Thy flock and fold of thy mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Church is heere on earth: gather them together, ſhield and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6766:20"/>ſhelter them by thy out-ſtretched Arme, that they may make thy kingdome known to be as it is, great and glorious. O ſuffer not the ſufferings of thy Saints ſtill to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, leſt the enemies of thy kingdom grow more proud and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous. Thou in thy eternall wiſdome and counſell conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, that the choſen children of thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome muſt be as gold purified in the fire of affliction; that ſo they may manifeſt the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6766:20"/>of thy kingdome; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y prayers, perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on, patience and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erance. Yet the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of thy trueth, who ſeeke their owne glorie by thy diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our, tread downe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy vineyard, to the ende it may bring forth no more fruit. But thy Kingdome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>annot bee deſtroyed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hough the members <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hereof may for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ime bee defaced. Thou canſt build vp <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ruines when man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>annot reſtore it. Shew thy ſelfe a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6766:21"/>as thou art a Builder of thine owne Kingdome, in the Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale. Shew vs the vvay vnto thy Kingdome. Teach vs the trueth: teach vs to preſerue it, and to preferre it as a pillar of thy Kingdome, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſafegard of our owne liues: So ſhall thy Kingdome of thy grace come, and bee conſerued by vs; that we may come vnto thy Kingdome of Glorie. Thy Son our Sauiour ſaid, His
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6766:21"/>Kingdome was not of this world: becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t was not tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but eternall; it was not earthly, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eauenly: yet his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer being thine, thy Kingdome is heere by Creation and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation: It is in Heauen by all ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of glorie and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rayſes. O let the Kingdome and Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of thy word come vnto vs; rule and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect our hearts heere on earth, that wee may come to thy Kingdome in heauen:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6766:22"/>That heere wee may obey and ſerue thee in this thy kingdome, and heereafter enioy thy happineſſe, and giue thee glory in in thine euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:6766:22"/>
               <head>Thy Will bee done in Earth, as it is in Heauen.</head>
               <p>Moſt gracious and glorious Soueraigne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy will and thy wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome are the ſame: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n wiſdome haſt thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one all things, Thy wiſdom hath wroght <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll; Thy Word hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>euealed thy will and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy wiſedome. Thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n thy vvonderfull
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6766:23"/>workes of Creation, diddeſt command all things to bee done, and it was done. Our wills (good Lord) are weake in that which is good, and ſtrong to doe euill. In Heauen all things obey thee, and vpon earth Man is moſt diſobedient to thy Maieſtie. The Earth brings foorth fruites for the ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of man; and man is fertil in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth ſinne to thy diſpleaſure and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. It is thy will, that wee ſhould ſerue
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6766:23"/>thee: but our wilfull deſires draw vs from thy ſeruice: So in earth &amp; earthly crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is contention and corruption: In Heauen and heauenly minded men is vnitie, concord, and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Heauen giues thee glory: Earth yeelds vs fruits. The fruits of the earth not well and thankefully vſed, turne to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes of our bodies &amp; foules. As thy good will hath wrought all things for our good: ſo (good Lord) giue
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6766:24"/>vs good wills, to doe thy will, whileſt wee liue heere on earth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that wee may make i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as a foot-ſtep to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſcend vnto Heauen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Let it therefore bee our chiefeſt deſire to conforme our willes to thy bleſſed will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> That when our Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage is paſſed heere vpon Earth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and wee haue paſſed through the vale o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> miſerie, thou mayeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> prouide for vs a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting place in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, that wee may bee ſeated with thy
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6766:24"/>Saints, to doe thee ſeruice, and to ſing vnto thee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:6766:25"/>
               <head>Giue vs this Day our daily Bread.</head>
               <p>THIS Day (O Lord) as all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther daies of our frail<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and fading life, being ſhort, and a ſpace wherein we ſtill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſinne. We ſtand in need of ſuſtenance. Our daily bread; and food being the mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to maintain our liues we cannot haue it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thou afford it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:6766:25"/>and when wee haue it, wee doe not afford thee deſerued praiſes. Thou haſt afforded vs plentie, and yet of our thankfulneſſe there is great penury. Wee ryot in exceſſe, and ſuffer thy ſeruants to ſuſtaine wants. We haue not onely bread, food, and rayment, but all things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie from thy liberall hands, and yet wee neither returne thee laud, nor to our nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die neighbors ſupply out of the ſtore thou haſt ſent vs. O Lord
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6766:26"/>as thou haſt comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs with thy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: ſo teach vs to make a right vſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them, that wee abuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not thy bountie i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> miſpending them, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reſtraine our Chari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tie, in releeuing thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> who are in greateſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> neceſſitie, accordin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the meanes which in mercie thou ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> giuen vs. Wee hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> need of food for ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Soules, and othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> things neceſſarie, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> well for our liues a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for our bodies. O giu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vs (good God) thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:6766:26"/>day, and at all other times, what is conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient both for our ſoules and bodies: and therewith graunt vs contentment and moderation, that wee may be ſatisfied with what is ſufficient, and not ſeeke things ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous to abuſe or miſpend that we haue: So wee hauing ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, may not onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee ſatisfied, but may do good therewith to our owne ſoules, and ſpare that which may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee ſpared vnto the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oore, forwhom thou
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6766:27"/>haſt not prouided. And ſo not onely this day, but all the dayes of our liues, wee may be good Stewards of thy bleſſings, and true Accomptants of thy earthly and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:6766:27"/>
               <head>Forgiue vs our Treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as wee forgiue them that treſpaſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs.</head>
               <p>HOW often and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally wee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thy Heauenly Maieſtie, thou (good God) onely, that feeſt all things, doeſt beſt dilcer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. Wee ſinne hourely, and therfore haue ſtill need of thy
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6766:28"/>pardon. Wee often deſire it, and do more often offend: Wee deſire it with condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet we ſeldome performe the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. How fearefull is our ſtate when wee commit ſinnes, craue pardon, promiſe to remitt others treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and yet neither avoide the euill, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend our liues, or paſſe by with pardon the ſmalleſt harmes wee haue from our Brethren, but ſeeke releaſe from thee, and reuenge againſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6766:28"/>them: <hi>O good God,</hi> teach vs to looke backe vnto our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer backeſlidings, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in this behalfe. And if there bee any whoſe faultes wee haue not remitted, done onely againſt our ſelues. Mooue our hearts to relent, and to bee reconciled as farre foorth as may ſtand with thy glory and the good of thy Church. If the cauſe bee ſuch as may not bee concealed, or kept from queſtion: Yet let not our particular
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6766:29"/>reuenge be the ground to ſeeke any mans ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine. But ſo teach and temper our hearts to diſtinguiſh betwixt priuate ſpleene &amp; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Iuſtice, thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, &amp; our owne vaine glory, wrath or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, as this our daylie prayer, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing others, be not made vnfruitfull vnto them, or hurtfull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our owne ſoules, but by pardoninge their leſſer offences thou mayſt be moued to pardon our greater ſinnes, and that for
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6766:29"/>thy ſake, and the ſafety of our ſoules through Ieſus Chriſt our LORD, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:6766:30"/>
               <head>And leade vs not into Temptation. But de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vs from euill:</head>
               <p>LEade vs not, or rather (Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God) ſuffer vs not to be ledd into temptation: we leade our ſelues, our Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence and naturall corruptions leade vs, The fleſh, the World and the Deuill lead vs &amp; driue vs vnto temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6766:30"/>What helpe, or what hold haue we in our ſelues, good God? When that which is without, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayles, that which is within vs is more ready to be ouercome then to withſtand: Nay, our inward, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, inbred corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, giues and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues, and therefore canot withſtand theſe aſſaults. Our fleſh is pampered and puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed vp with Pride. Our luſts riſing from our naturall inſtigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the fleſh, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6766:31"/>prouocations of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, procured by internall inflamations, and externall incenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, lead vs and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerwhelme vs with temptations. When we (good Lord) as we are directed, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thee not to leade vs, or ſuffer vs to bee lead into temptation: we therein craue thy deliuerances from the frailty of our fleſh, which cannot reſiſt, but ray ſeth temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Our Captiuity comes from our ſelu, our Deliuerance from
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6766:31"/>thee: Wee are daily, hourely, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally aſſaulted with temptations of luſts, when wee doe but ſee or feele that wherein we delight: Of pride, when exalted, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to bee exalted, wee climbe higher then our ſtrength, or capacitie can reach vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; or if comming vnto it, and comming by vngodly meanes vnto it: we fall (good Lord) from thy grace further and further, as at the firſt wee fell from it, when wee
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6766:32"/>ſought not from the ſacred Counſels of thy holy Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, which way wee ſhould walke.</p>
               <p>Our Temptations, (O bleſſed reſiſter and reſtrainer of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter) are, either ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, wherein our fleſh and frailty, eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffers vs to be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized: or elſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued; and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, wherein wee cannot without thy heauenly aſſiſtance, maintaine the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, or continue the Conflict. In all theſe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6766:32"/>wee are weake, and thou (O Lord) art ſtrong; ſtrengthen our weakeneſſe, ſuſtaine vs againſt Sathan: Suffer vs not to bee ſurprized: Repulſe him by re-uniting thy heauenly Spirit vnto our fraile fleſh; ſtregthening vs when we cannot ſtand, and reſtoring vs when we are fallen. O Lord, Thou onely art able to deliuer vs from dangers both of body and ſoule. Our tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations comes from both: Our naturall
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6766:33"/>corruptions in the body, our infuſed contagions in the ſoule, had neede of thy ayde to defend and deliuer vs from temptations. Our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance comes from thee, that our prayſes and thankſgiuing may returne vnto thee. O deliuer, ſaue, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend vs from the ſuggeſtions of Sathan. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:6766:33"/>
               <head>For thine is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Power, Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</head>
               <p>THe Kingdoms and Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Earth (moſt mighty Lord) are thine in Creation, power, praiſe, and Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. It is thine (O LORD) for thou haſt firſt framed it:
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6766:34"/>It is thine, for thou doſt conſerue, and preſetue it: It is thine, for thou doſt rule and gouerne the Vniuerſe: Thy Sonne hath ſaid, His Kingdome vvas not of this Worlde, becauſe he would not rule viſibly, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally, but ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and eternally. Yet thou haſt giuen him power in heauen and in earth to redeeme ſinners, and to ſaue ſinnefull men: What Kingdome can bee greater, more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and firme? What
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6766:34"/>power can bee more ample, or ſo benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all? What glory can ſhine more in and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the firmament of Heauen? O there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, by that thy po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer bring vs vnto this thy Kingdome: where wee may haue reſt without trouble, comfort without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention: ioy without end: and thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt receiue kingdome without reſiſtance, Power without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution: Glorie without deniall: and Dominion without
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6766:35"/>diſobedience: To this thy Kingdome, by thine owne power bring vs to giue thee glory, and to be true ſubiects of thy domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: for thine owne, for thy Sonne, and for thy ſeruants ſake, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:6766:35"/>
               <head>One Prayer framed vpon all the parts of the Lords Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</head>
               <p>MOſt mightie God, moſt mercifull Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Thou art not onely in Heauen by thy preſence, but in Heauen and Earth by thy power: Thou in thy mercy haſt vouſchſafed to chooſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6766:36"/>and accompt vs for thy children. Wee by our tranſgreſſions haue failed to doe the duties of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Thou art in heauen and beholdeſt vs; We are on earth and are ſo earthly minded, that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not behold and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, as wee ſhould thy Maieſty, thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and thy Iuſtice: Thy Name is hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and holy, yet we take thy name in vaine; diſhonour it, and thereby deſtroy our own ſoules: Thy
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6766:36"/>Kingdome is already come both in heauen, and in the hearts of the Regenerate. O graunt vs regenerate hearts, that wee may come vnto thee, and vnto thy kingdome. Thy Will (O good and gracious God) is that they whom thou haſt ordayned to bee Saints in Heauen, ſhould bee holy, and ſo ſerue thee, to doe thy will here on earth that they may attaine to thy heauenly inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance. But alas, how doe wee tranſgreſſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6766:37"/>the will, breake thy lawes, and follow our owne willes. O yet here make vs Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and fulfillers of thy holy will, that hereafter we may bee partakers of thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly poſſeſſions.</p>
               <p>Thou giueſt vs (good Lord) dayly bread, foode, and ſuſtenance; wee (as we haue neede) dayly deſire the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance thereof. Wee come with hands to receiue, but not with hearts to render pray <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for theſe thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:6766:37"/>O let our daies to come be as full of thankefullneſſe, as thoſe paſt haue bene of vnthankefullneſſe. Teach vs day by day to deſire not onely corporall, but ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all foode, holyly to vſe and not fleſhly to abuſe either of both. That we may not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire our meat to pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per our bodies, and to prouoke them to luſt: but to liue ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly, to take ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and to auoide ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. That wee ſeeke not ſpirituall foode
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6766:38"/>onely to ſeeme to be, but indeed to be true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly religious.</p>
               <p>Our treſpaſſes (moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mercifull Father) are great, infinite, and grieuous. Wee come to thee, and wee cry to thee for forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Thou, O Lord art ready to remi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them vpon our repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: Wee goe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with our ſinnes, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not with ſorrow fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hauing committed them, with promiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of pardon vnto other who haue offende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vs; and yet wee for
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:6766:38"/>giue not them as wee deſire to bee forgiuen. This is the cauſe that wee neither receiue pardon, nor amende our ſinnefull liues: And this is the cauſe of our preſent hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our hearts, and will bee of our future greater puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, except thou in thy mercy forget and forgiue our former treſpaſſes, make vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hereafter to amend them, and make vs charitable to forgiue the treſpaſſes of our brethren offending vs,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:6766:39"/>as we doe thee: It is not thou (gracious God) that leadeſt vs into temptations, but wee are ledd into them by our owne luſtes and infirmities, wee fall into them by our owne fraileties, wee are inuited by the inticements o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> others, and by the ſubtiltie of Satan. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou (good God) doſt ſuffer and no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuſtaine vs, wee no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> onely receiue, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> runne headlong into temptations, and eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſincke vnder the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:6766:39"/>Before wee know where we ſtand, we fall: and can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther withſtand, nor riſe vp againe, except thou helpe vs: O bee thou our ſupporter &amp; ſtrength: Arme our ſoules, our hearts, and our conſciences, ſo ſhall wee bee ſafe vnder thy ſaluation, and bee couered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the wings of thy moſt mercifull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection: The euills that come to vs are from the euills that are within vs, and are intertained by vs: The
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:6766:40"/>euill affections of our hearts threaten to pull vpon vs corporall, temporall, ſpirituall, and eternall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. O keepe vs from the euill of our offences and ſinnes, that wee may ſhunne the euill of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the ſame, that ſo wee may not feele the weight of thy power and indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, but may here ſo be ſubiect &amp; obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to thy Dominion, that wee may hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enter into the ioyes of that celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:6766:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>kingdome, which is thine, and which thou haſt prepared for ſuch as truely ſerue thee heere, and ſhall bee bleſſed Saints in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:6766:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:6766:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Certaine ſhort Prayers and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations vpon the ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</head>
            <div type="preamble">
               <head>I am the Lord thy God that brought thee out of Bon dage.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince thou, O Lord GOD, great and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:6766:42"/>haſt brought vs from bondage, not onely corporall, but from ſpirituall and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall captiuitie, by ſending thy Sonne, our Sauiour, to ſuffer for our ſinnes. Suffer vs not (O gracious God) to fall againe into worſe then the Aegyptian bondage of Idolatry, Infidelitie, Superſtition, and Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance. Teach vs only truely and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to adore thee our euerliuing God, and our God that giueſt life. Let vs not (O
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:6766:42"/>Lord) doubt, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt of thy power or prouidence, but that our faith may bee firme, our hope aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and our confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in thee alwaies conſtant, to expect the good pleaſure in performance of thy gracious promiſes: but that I may loue and honour thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, and more then all creatures which are corruptible, the workemanſhip of thy hands, and which as they haue their being from thee, ſo they
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:6766:43"/>can not bee at all, or ſubſiſt without thy ſuſtentation. As thou art. (O Lord) graunt that wee may honour thee as thou art our God, that wee may praiſe thee World without end, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="commandment">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:6766:43"/>
               <head>Thou ſhalt haue no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gods but me.</head>
               <p>THe Heathen, O LORD GOD euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, giue thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vnto ſtickes, ſtones, and other imaginary, idle, vaine, and euill things. The Infidels and vnbeleeuers doe either openly, or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly deny thy Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and diuine incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:6766:44"/>Majeſtie. The ignorant and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill inſtructed people, though they by cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome profeſſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of thy ſeruice and power, yet they know not what it is, but either through e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill inſtruction, or for want of inſtruction, know not, or care not how to keepe thy Commandements, O Lord, teach them that beleeue amiſſe, the wayes of truth, and to amend their errors, thoſe that beleeue not, touch their hearts,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:6766:44"/>make them to tremble at thy terrors, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Iuſtice, which yet they feele not, and ſo to entertaine Faith, that their ſoules may be ſaued. Teach vs that profeſſe thy truth to practiſe it, That we may haue none other Gods but thee, the True and onely Euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuing GOD: There is none other but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thou that art good, and goodneſſe it ſelfe. How then ſhall wee ſtand in iudgement before thee, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre and accompt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:6766:45"/>any created thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of thee. O let our knees and hearts bow downe before thee alone, with faith, with feare, and with acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Then we ſhall haue none other Gods but thee; neither fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low our owne fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, nor the corrupt doctrine of ſuch as miſleade others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="commandment">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:6766:45"/>
               <head>Thou ſhalt not make vnto thy ſelfe the Image or likeneſſe of any thing in Heauen above, or in the Earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath, or in the Waters vnder the Earth: For, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>AS thy power, O LORD is greateſt, and thy preheminence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all thy Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:6766:46"/>in the heauens, and in the earth: So is thine Honour ſo precious, that thou wouldeſt not haue it giuen to any thing in heauen or in in earth. Yet (good Lord) our natures are ſo fraile, and our ſoules ſo ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, that wee fancie and frame vnto our ſelues imaginary wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe of creatures in Heauen, in earth, and in the waters, by their ſimilitude and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; giuing, or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing thy glory to thoſe glowormes
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:6766:46"/>being falſe and fading fantaſies of our owne imaginations: Since then moſt mighty Maker and Monarch of heauen and earth, thou ſeeſt our frailtie to fall, and the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of thy Maieſtie, by falſe worſhip; by framing the likeneſſe of any creature to worſhip: O ſuffer vs not to make, to ſet vp, or to adore falſe Gods, to fall before them, to place any power, or hope in them, to truſt to our owne policie or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer:
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:6766:47"/>to depend vpon earthly helpes, ioyes, or delights, but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly onely vpon thy ſtrength, good will and pleaſure: That nothing in heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, in the earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath, or in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters vnder the earth, may carry vs from thy true worſhip and ſeruice, which is our ſafety, and concernes thy glory, to whom be giuen praiſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ceaſing, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour without Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, now and for euer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="commandment">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:6766:47"/>
               <head>Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vaine.</head>
               <p>O Lord GOD moſt mighty and merciful, ſince thy maieſtie is ſo high, great, and glorious, how care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſhould wee be to conſerue a reuerend and awefull eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy holy name,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:6766:48"/>as to honour it in thought, word, and deed: But, O moſt gracious God, how careleſſe are wee to keep thy holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement: How ready by irreligion to blaſpheme thy holy Name with oathes, curſes, execrations, to abuſe thy holy Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, in forſwearing, and falſe accuſing, to name thee (O our good GOD) in our mouthes, when wee haue thee not in our hearts, to diſſemble and make Hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:6766:48"/>profeſſion of thy holy and true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without any care or conſcience to put it in practiſe. O moſt mightie and mercifull God, we beſeech thee to pardon and paſſe by our profaneneſſe, in taking thy name in vaine, our impiety in blaſpheming thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly name, our raſhneſſe in naming thee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out inward reuerence, or remembrance of thy power, honour, and Maieſtie; our proneſſe to mention thy Word, Workes,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:6766:49"/>and Worſhip, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out due premed tati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and conſideration. O teach vs when wee talke, thinke or inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate thy holy name, to doe it with conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, faith, and ſeare, when we thinke on it, to cogitate and call to memory that wee are in thy preſence, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that wee are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy power, and ſubiect to thy puniſhment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="commandment">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:6766:49"/>
               <head>Remember that thou keepe holy the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath Day: ſixe dayes, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>SInce thou (moſt glorious God) by thine omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent power haſt created this World, and by thy provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, for a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all memoriall of this thy moſt wonderfull Worke, haſt or dained
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:6766:50"/>a Sabbath, or ſeaueth day of reſt, to bee ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated and ſet apart for thy Seruice. In which wee ſhould be free from ſeruile workes, and worldly cares O LORD, therefore ſanctifie vs, and ſo prepare our heartes for this thy ſeruice, that we may make a conſcience of performing this thy Precept: For this purpoſe, Let vs bee carefull to keepe thy Sabbaothes in publique in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:6766:50"/>of thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, by Prayer, prayſes, and hearing of thy Word: In priuate, by Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Meditation, Conference, Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of thy Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie; and Workes of Creation and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, as in deeds of Charitie, Mercie, and Compaſſion to the needy. For this ende (good and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious GOD) fitte and furniſh our hearts, our wits and our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, with Zeale, Knowledge,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:6766:51"/>and Conſcience to ſhake off on this thy holy Sabbaths, ſloth, and ſlownes to come vnto thine Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, and to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe theſe religious Duties, to caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way worldly cares, bodily labours, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſuch as are for neceſſitie, for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent preſeruation of things ready to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, which cannot bee otherwiſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented, or longer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, and of that which may with moſt Moderation ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:6766:51"/>the religious Exerciſes and holy Duties of that Day. Theſe Graces graunt vs, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="commandment">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:6766:52"/>
               <head>Honour thy Father and thy Mother, that thy, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>O Lord God, as thou art the Propagator, and Protector of our ſoules, to whom on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we ſhould giue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Honour: ſo wouldſt thou that we ſhould giue to our naturall Parents, reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, obedience, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenance,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:6766:52"/>and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, which in Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is due for the cauſe of our birth, being, education and maintenance by them: And that we may doe this which thou (good God) requireſt; Wee beſeech thee, remoue from vs Pride, ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceite, and ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loue, neglect of our dutie to our Parents, and Superiours: im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience, when they ſhall exerciſe autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, inflict puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or demaund thoſe things to bee
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:6766:53"/>done, which we doe diſlike, or not deſire; Hardneſſe of heart, when they ſtand in neede of our helpe. O Lord, graunt that wee ouerweane not our ſelues, thinking our ſelues wiſer then our Parents, Teachers, Magiſtrates or Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, but that wee may performe all their lawfull Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out grudging or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laying<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, leſt by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience we diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour them, procure thy curſe, thy diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:6766:53"/>and our own dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Let vs not bee like to curſed <hi>Cam,</hi> the diſcouerer of his Fathers nakedneſſe: But that wee may ſo keepe this thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, that in honouring them wee may receiue honour from thee; and that happines which thou haſt promiſed, that our dayes may bee long and bleſſed not onely in this Land which thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs to liue heere vpon earth, but euen in the Land of the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:6766:54"/>Liuing, where thou doſt raigne for euer: and where we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in thy glorious preſence euermore to giue thee Praiſe, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="commandment">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:6766:54"/>
               <head>Thou ſhalt doe no Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</head>
               <p>MOſt merciful GOD, that giueſt life, &amp; deſireſt not the death of ſinners, nor that wee by ſinne, or vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, ſhould ſlay our owne ſoules, or our Brethren, that beare thine Image. Wee beſeech thee to teach vs wherein wee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:6766:55"/>murther, by our hands, tongues, or hearts, that ſo wee may ſhunne the ſinne and puniſhment that followeth the ſame. O Lord wee ſlay our owne ſoules by our manifold and great ſinnes; wee murther other mens ſoules by cauſing them to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſinnes; by which wee take from our ſelues, and them, the life of grace: O Lord we ſlay our ſoules by extinguiſhing the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirations of thy holy ſpirit, not ſuffering it
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:6766:55"/>to purge our ſinnes by Prayer and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, not receiuing or retaining, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecting thoſe good motions and holy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, which thy grace giues vnto vs. Wee commit Murther, if not of the liues of men) yet of their good Names. In our hearts by Anger, Wrath, and Enuy: with our tongues, by ſlander, reproach, ſowing of ſedition, curſing, and euill ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, with our hands done vpon the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:6766:56"/>of our ſelues by Violence, Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Adultery and other Diſtempers: whereby either the ſoules or liues of our ſelues, or of others, are deſtroyed, by not ſuccouring them, as wee are able, with counſell, correction, or charitable reliefe, when they ſtand in need of vs: by theſe &amp; many other waies, moſt mercifull GOD, we murther either our own ſoules or bodies, or the ſoules and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours:
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:6766:56"/>O Lord God, therefore who haſt giuen vs ſoules and bodies, giue vs grace and aſſiſtance not to deſtroy them in our ſelues or others, but purifie our hearts and affections, inlighten our vnderſtandings, kindle zeale to thy glory and truth, which may ſaue our owne ſoules, and ſettle vs to ſeeke the ſaluation of others: and not to be a meanes of our own, or of other mens ſubuerſions: Plant in our hearts Charitie
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:6766:57"/>Meekeneſſe, and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifulneſſe towards all men, ſobriety in our deſires, carriage, and conuerſations: a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſeeke the good, and not the hurt of our Neighbours: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue from vs Pride, Preſumption, Cruelty and hardnes of heart, whereby we ſlay our owne ſoules, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the liues, eſtate or eſtimation of our brethren; So wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus fenced by the grace and good gifts of thy holy Spirit, with faith and feare
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:6766:57"/>to offend thy Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, may thereby learne to keepe this thy holy Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, to the ſauing, and not the deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſoules and liues of our ſelues and others: Graunt this good Lord, for thy mercies ſake, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="commandment">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:6766:58"/>
               <head>Thou ſhalt not commit Adulterie.</head>
               <p>O Lord GOD, thou by thy holy Word haſt taught vs, that there is ſpirituall and corporall Adultery. Thou haſt comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not to commit them: Yet our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt natures drawe vs to both: We forſake thee, our God, the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:6766:58"/>true Spouſe of our ſoules, by adhering in confidence, worſhip or diſordinate affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble creatures, and ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterating thy ſeruice and Worſhip, become forgetfull of thee, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing more our own luſts, pleaſures, or profits, then thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts: O God, full of power who haſt created vs thy poore creatures, who ſeeſt and ſearcheſt the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret corners of our hearts, vnſearchable and ſecret vnto our
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:6766:59"/>ſelues. Cleanſe theſe ſecret, yet ſtrong and preuailing luſts which drawe vs to commit the Spirituall and Carnall Adultery: reſtraine our vnchaſte lookes, and inticing aſpects one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Cauſe vs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraine wanton ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, to abſtaine from Drunkennes, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of Diet, (which are the Inſtrumentes and prouocation to I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, To forbeare pampering of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. Gorgiouſnes &amp; Curioſity of apparell
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:6766:59"/>which drawes vs to ouer-much delight of our ſelues, and to a deſire to defile our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, with Adultery, Fornication, &amp; other filthy beſtiall Conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating of our owne bodies, corrupting of others and breaking the boundes of this thy holy Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement. That wee ſhould not commit Adultery ſpirituall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, or corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall againſt one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and both againſt thy Lawes. Keepe vs therefore, O Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:6766:60"/>Lord, within the compaſſe of this thy holy Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, by thine own power and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. By, and for which onely we ſhall be able to giue thee laude and glory now, and for euer. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="commandment">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:6766:60"/>
               <head>Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</head>
               <p>THou, O gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious GOD, who haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs ſufficiencie, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireſt of vs conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedneſſe with that we haue: And though we thinke wee haue leſſe then wee neede, and haue much leſſe then wee deſire: yet thou, O our good God, the giver of all
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:6766:61"/>wee haue, doeſt onely know what is beſt for vs: Our ſeuerall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates haue neede of meanes for mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, according to our callings, but wee doe not rightly mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the lawfull and right means by which wee ſhould come to this competency, wee go by vngodly means to ſeeke it, wee one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weigh what wee would haue, but doe not conſider ſo well where and how it may be godly, and lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gotten, which
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:6766:61"/>makes vs to take from our Neighbours, and others what belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vnto them. O Lord therefore take from vs Couetouſnes, the roote of deceit and falſe dealing, ſtealthes of things we want, or would haue. Extortion to get any thing by colour of Iuſtice, and bribing to pervert Iuſtice. Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence to take any thing by force, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, or ſtrong hand from others; Negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and ſlothfulnes in our ſeuerall eſtates
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:6766:62"/>and callings, which breede beggery, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, and robbery. Send vs lawfull, chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and honeſt care to prouide things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, coſening, or double dealing: diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, and frugality in the diſpoſing of our Eſtates, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee may prouide things needefull with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſome to others, or forced to ſteale or purloine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. Graunt, good Lord, therefore that our endeauor may be
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:6766:62"/>to get what is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for our ſelues, without doing wrong vnto others: Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in our callings, without ouermuch care, cruelty, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, or circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention. Iuſt dealing with all men: Fruga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie without miſerie, Contentedneſſe with our eſtates, And if we haue plenty, to vſe it prouidently, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably, auoyding mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery or miſpending, not ſeeking any thing by vniuſt or vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meanes, nor kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:6766:63"/>it by frande or falſehood. O Lord GOD, graunt that wee robbe not thee of thine honour, by ſtealing from our ſelues in ſloth and ſecurity, that time which wee ſhould ſpend in thy ſeruice but that we may keep this thy holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement with care and conſcience, to thy honour, and our owne ſaluation, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="commandment">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:6766:63"/>
               <head>Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</head>
               <p>THou, O Lord, that art the God of truth, and teacheſt vs to maintaine truth, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeſt vs to beare falſe witneſſe to the loſſe, diſcredit, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance, or ſhame of our Neighbours: that
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:6766:64"/>wee neither ſlaunder them with our tongs, accuſe them, by oath or word, wrongfully; thinke or iudge euill of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without cauſe, Deceiue them by fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery or Hipocryſie, backebite any, nor boulſter any bad cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes by countenance, cunning, or giue ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine and raſh beliefe vnto rayſers of ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or euill reports: that wee teach not falſe doctrine in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of faith; nor vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olate faith, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe with any man to
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:6766:64"/>their deluſion and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt: but that wee may avoyde the perill and puniſhment of breaking this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement. Teach vs moſt iuſt and wiſe GOD, to make Conſcience of our words, aſwell as our workes, to avoide ſlaunder, falſe accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to ſpeake the truth, to bee ſincere, and ſingle-hearted, when we come, or are called to giue teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the truth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect of perſons, profit, friendſhip, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:6766:65"/>reuenge, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, that wee may knowe and conſider, we are alwayes in thy preſence, and vnder thy power to bee pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, if wee tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe theſe thy holy precept. That wee may ſay and ſweare the truth in all things, ſince all that we ſay, ſweare, or doe, is in thy ſight, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to thy ſeuere and vncorrupted Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Graunt and giue vs grace by thy po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to doe this for
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:6766:65"/>thy glory and our owne good, thou gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious God to whom be praiſe, for euer and euer, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="commandment">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:6766:66"/>
               <head>Thou ſhalt not covet thy Neighbours houſe: his Wife, his ſeruant, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>SInce thou, our Soueraign Lord and God, haſt giuen vs all that wee haue, knoweſt what is needfull for vs to haue and keepeſt for vs that thou haſt giuen. Thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeſt we ſhould ſubdue our luſtfull thoughts, and deſires,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:6766:66"/>of coueting that which is not ours: and bee content with that thou art pleaſed to make ours. O make vs (moſt mercifull God) moderate in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring, ſober in vſing, and abſtinent from concupiſcence, and coveting thoſe things that belong not vnto vs: Suffer not our wanton eyes to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, our corrupt hearts to couet, or our looſe thoughts to bee led with inticements of worldly, vaine, and tranſitory things
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:6766:67"/>which may make vs to cover any thing that thou haſt given, and doth belong to others, and not vnto our ſelues, whether it be the perſons eſtates, lives, liberties, ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or duties of our Neighbours; be they our Superiors, equals, or inferiors. O Lord God, holy and iuſt, to this ende clenſe our Conſeiences, reſtraine our appetites and evil affections; chaſtiſe our inordinate deſires, ſubdue our luſtfull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammations: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:6766:67"/>our vnbridled corruptions. Send thy holy and heauenly ſpirit into our hearts, to take the poſſeſſion and protection of our poore ſinnefull ſoules, that wee be not ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, but may be kept as cleaue veſſels, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified for thy ſeruice to keepe this, and all thy Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, for thy mercies ſake, for thy merits, &amp; tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the Mediation of thy Son our Lord and Sauiour.</p>
               <p>O LORD, if our Houſes be but poore,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:6766:68"/>let vs not covet to make them better, by ſeeking that which belongs not vnto vs, or by getting that which we cannot law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully haue: If our ſtore be ſmall, ſuffer vs not to ſeeke that which wee ſhould not ſeeke; either our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Wiues by A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, inticements, or carnall prouocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or any of his goods, by oppreſſion, deceit or any kinde of corruption, his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, by fraude, flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, or falſe dealing:
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:6766:68"/>But doe thou, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious God, ſettle our ſoules to contentment with what wee haue, or may obtaine by induſtry, voyde of iniury; by lawefull meanes without vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull practiſes, with conſcience, modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſobrietie; that ſhunning to ſeeke and covet that which is not ours: we may heere faithfully ſerue thee, ſet foorth thy glory, and heereafter receiue eternall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe with thee in Heauen. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:6766:69"/>
            <head>My Mementoes which I ſhould make to my ſelfe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>THe conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of my ſinnes, generall, and: particular; by prayer, and by repentance.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>The Examination of my life, how it hath beene lead, either in goodneſſe, or in
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:6766:69"/>looſeneſſe of liuing.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>Whether I haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended or conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in any known groſſe ſinnes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 <hi>What they are, how they haue their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning &amp; growth</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5 <hi>What reſiſtance I haue made, and what ſucceſſe that hath had.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6 <hi>Whether I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled thoſe ſinnes, and whether they haue againe retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7 <hi>What hopes or means I haue to baniſh thoſe, or the like
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:6766:70"/>ſinnes?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>8 <hi>Whether my prayers befainter or ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; more frequent or ſeldomer then they haue beene?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>9 <hi>Whether my diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, doubts, and dulneſſe, in the time of prayer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, or be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooued.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>10 <hi>Whether thoſe Paſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which were more preualent in me are yet pacified</hi>
               </item>
               <item>11 <hi>Whether I cannot yet heartily for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue, and pray for thoſe that haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iured
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:6766:70"/>mee.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>12 <hi>Whether my want of Loue and Charitie to my Neighbours be yet amended?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>13 <hi>Whether I haue ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Faith with Examination, and that with Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>There is no day wherein I liue, but I ſhould call my ſelfe to accompt, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow ſome time in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of my ſelf, to ſee and ſearch, which of theſe, or the like ſinnes I haue
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:6766:71"/>committed, which of them I haue corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted: what yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines to bee done, that I may no more doe them: And if I can fall to theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrances by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act repetition, I ſhall ſooner come to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: If I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not altogeter remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them, yet I muſt firſt reade them in theſe, or the like lines, then anſwere to euery Article, as if I were examined be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſtrickeſt Iudge for any capitall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:6766:71"/>or elſe I may be aſſured I ſhall come at laſt before a ſeuere and all-ſeeing Iudge, who knowes and will iudge all: when I haue done this, I muſt goe to prayer for the remoouing of theſe euills; the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in doing better: Or if I finde I cannot doe it, I muſt ſtill pray that I may bee able to doe it.</p>
            <p>Theſe Meditations and the Prayers fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing them, being the beſt Medicines to cure all the maladies
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:6766:72"/>of my minde and ſoule: for which end, and to attaine to that holy and happy ende, It is neceſſarie that I ſhould frame vnto my ſelfe, if not vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſome ſhort ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe following or the like.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:6766:72"/>
            <head>A Prayer for perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Points.</head>
            <p>O Lord GOD, my ſinnes are great &amp; grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous, many and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit in number: they are ſo many that I cannot reckon or remember them. Thoſe that I doe remember, which are the feweſt in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the reſt; I
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:6766:73"/>haue not confeſſed or acknowledged as I ſhould doe.</p>
            <p>I haue not exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned my ſinnefull life that I haue ledde, nor ſought amendment of the ſame, I haue not looked into the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning or grouth of my ſinnes, nor how I haue reſiſted the ſame, or if at any time I haue done it, yet I haue fallen more backewards then I went forwards. My hope of reſiſtance is nothing but in thy power and mercy, O
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:6766:73"/>therefore moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull God, Graunt me power not onely to proceede in exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, but in amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers good God which ſhould be the pathway to thy praiſe, and the ſteppes to my ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; they are feeble and ſlow. O make them ſtronger and more frequent. Take from me in my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers diſtractions, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and dullneſſe. Remooue my moſt violent paſſions, the perturbers of minde
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:6766:74"/>and ſoule. Grant me grace to forgiue them that wrong mee, and that I may pray for them that perſecute mee, as thy ſonne my Sauiour did and hath taught mee to doe And as thy ſeruan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Stephen</hi> hath ſhewed me an example: Take from me hatred, and increaſe in mee lou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and charity: Graun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mee grace to ioyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> faith with examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and examination with repentance: And that I may be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter able to do this and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:6766:74"/>all other good duties, Giue me power to pray vnto thee and to prayſe thee: So be it Good Lord <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:6766:75"/>
            <head>The Differences in Deuotion and exerciſes of Religion betwixt the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and the <hi>Romane</hi> Catholicks.</head>
            <head type="sub">Eſpecially in regard of <hi>Exceſſe</hi> and <hi>Defect.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FOr the exceſſe: The Romaniſts tye themſelues too much vnto Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall howers as they
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:6766:75"/>call them, in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like or priuate ſeruice of God. As to ſay or ſing Maſſe at ſuch houres: as in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, at the howres of nine and eleauen to haue Angular Maſſes whereof many in one Church, and in diuers Corners of the ſame Church at the ſame time: To tye them in their priuate Deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to reade or rather to runne ouer the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Pſalter, and other manuall bookes here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore altogether in the Lati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e tongue,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:6766:76"/>which moſt of them vnderſtood not at all: So might they ſpeake as Birdes are taught to ſpeake, by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation, ſcarce of ſyllables aright; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ſaying one word or at the leaſt ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding one for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without any ſence or ſignification, to themſelues, what they ſpeake: But of latter times heere in England (though not ſo in other Countries, where the Roman Catholique Religion (as themſelues call it)
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:6766:76"/>onely hath vſe and force heere more then elſewhere,) They are lately tolerated by the authority of the Church of Rome to haue ſome few prayer bookes both in Latine and engliſh, but which of both they do moſt vſe, themſelues do beſt know. And either they are ſo full farced and ſtuffed with hymnes, ſhort verſicles; ſome without concluſion of ſence, and in moſt, the ſentences ſo ſhortly and ſuddainely ſet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, the one leap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:6766:77"/>ſo cloſe vpon the backe of the other, that hardly can they remember, or ſcarce perceiue what they ſay. Onely they are made to beleeue, that theſe ready, but raw repetitions may ſerue for Gods ſeruice, whereas the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſhould be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well ſupplyed as the affection, in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>Heerein is their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe ioyned with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: Exceſſe of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in heaping many
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:6766:77"/>words not well wey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Defect in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of what they doe deliuer:</p>
            <p>Beſides there is an exceeding great Error allowed and taught in putting them not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to pronounce thoſe prayers ſo peeced, which muſt needes be ouer perfunctorily thus ſpeeded: but ſome (nay many) I may ſay moſt of their prayers are directed to the Saints as interceſſors, whereof ſome were ſuch as in their liue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:6766:78"/>were ſcarce holy but ſo eſteemed, and yet were in a maner deifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, onely becauſe they adhered to the Pope of: Rome Namely (amongſt others) <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Becket</hi> ſometime Arch-Biſhop of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury, rebellious to his Soueraigne, and ſo though euill ſlayne therefore Canonized: Prayers allowed by publique authority printed and practiſed euen in our times. As deſiring God by the blood of this <hi>Becket</hi> to make the poore ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:6766:78"/>ſuppliant to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend where Chriſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended. They making in thoſe common prayer bookes more prayers to the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> then to our Sauiour himſelfe. They calling on her to beſeech God the Father: and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund God her ſonne by the right of a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Which with many other moſt groſſ ſuperſtitions, aſwell in their publicke, as in their priuate Deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, themſelues cannot deny; or if they ſhould,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:6766:79"/>yet their bookes are extant and their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes perſpicuous, Their creeping and their bending and bowing of their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies before the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of ſome but ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Saints. The a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doring of the Image of the Croſſe and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixe, with other, but ſaid to be but hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed reliques: what di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonor it hath broght to the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and what danger to themſelues, although they will not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and their lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedeſt
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:6766:79"/>Teachers will ſeeme to defend or to excuſe: yet Intelligent and pious men who are not ſeduced by Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits and Romiſh Prieſts, or ſo vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py as to be bred vp in their Schooles of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue though they wil not confeſſe; That de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion without true vnderſtanding, turnes ſoone vnto ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: That feruor with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Faith, and beliefe without knowledge, makes many men erre groſſely, and offend
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:6766:80"/>moſt where they think they doe beſt: Their bookes of Meditation are in many parts good to ſtirre Deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but in ſome places patched with ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>If this Cockle might be ſeparated from their Corne it would proouemore profitable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Proteſtants profeſſion &amp; practiſe of Religion, wherof I profeſſe to be one. If moſt Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts would be as feruent, &amp; as fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in their Praiers, as many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent in that they
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:6766:80"/>pray, they ſhould more ſhun ſinne, and ſhame the Romaniſts; who yet ſeeme to ſhun them by being more deuoute in that which they doe leſſe vnderſtand, and are far more frequent in Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. And if there were more zeale joyned with Conſcience, it would much adorne the profeſſion, &amp; make it moſt excellent as it is in deede, ſo would it be in eſtimation and effect. But no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion can make men perfect: The moſt
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:6766:81"/>perfection wee haue conſiſts or is conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated in practiſe and action. Peace and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie which ſhould helpe, doth yet hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Devotion. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets Pride, and that ingenders preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Affliction giues inſtruction, gaines hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, guides the Conſcience, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes euill liuing: Witneſſe, nay, many witneſſes heereof, were the perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Primitiue Church, when vnder the Tyrannies and
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:6766:81"/>bloudy Maſſacres of the Chriſtians, by the Heathen Emperours, Princes, and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates: the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans liues were ſhining lights of ſanctitie: their patient and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſufferings, cauſes of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſion to many men, who before knew not God, nor what Godlineſſe meant: Their ſinceritie and ſingleneſſe of heart ſet vp Trophees for themſelues, and made them Conquerors o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their cruelleſt and cauſeleſſe Enemies.
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:6766:82"/>And I would I could not ſay in mine owne particular, for my poore ſinnefull ſelfe, that when I enioyed the World as I did moſt wiſh, I was euer then worſt. I would I could as well ſay, that ſince Aduerſitie came, I became better: yet if any thing worke in mee, or in others, amendement, it muſt be Affliction, and ſome Aduerſitie. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffliction in minde for ſinne: and a touch of Aduerſitie for the ſame. O therefore
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:6766:82"/>that ſo I may doe as now I ſay, and that others may doe as I wiſh. My Prayers (I hope by the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſiſtancce) ſhall be, That yet in theſe times of Peace and Proſperity, whileſt our Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion (the beſt, becauſe the trueſt) is enioyed and eſtabliſhed, might by Gods permiſſion, and all helping power in theſe ſerene and and Sunſhining dayes before there come more darkeneſſe and danger, caſt off care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſenes
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:6766:83"/>of planting Truth, ſupplanting Errors; practiſing of Piety, preſeruing the publique peace and ſafetie; reforming of things amiſſe in the Church &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weale, which cannot be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our more diligence and vigilancie, cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, prouidence, and care; eſpecially by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the chief watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the Church and State more cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to their Stations, the one by Doctrine, Diſcipline, and Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence:
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:6766:83"/>the other by Counſell and Circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection to prevent perills, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the peace of this our Sion. And that this may bee perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, I conclude with the enſuing Prayer, that being the ſubiect of this ſmall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:6766:84"/>
            <head>A Prayer for the peace and proſperitie of the Kings Maieſtie, his Dominions, and Subiects.</head>
            <p>MOſt mighty, gracious, and merciful <hi>God</hi> who haſt made, doſt gouerne and preſerue the Heauens, the Earth, and all the Creatures therein co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained: Be mercifull
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:6766:84"/>vnto vs moſt miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſinnefull crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, who were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and yet doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more, or ſo much, as commit ſins againſt thy ſup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>came Majeſtie: Wee haue from the higheſt to the loweſt, beene pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted with originall ſinnes. Our great, our grieuous, and our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crying ſinnes call vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee for our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. But becauſe thy Mercy is aboue all thy other workes,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:6766:85"/>which yet exceede in greatneſſe. Wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate our ſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy Throne of grace; beſeeching thee for thy Sonnes ſake, and for thine owne goodneſſe ſake to ſaue vs poore ſinners, who deſire to doe thee ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, though hitherto wee haue gone aſtray: and walked in the waies of wickedneſſe: Thou haſt planted thy glorious Goſpell of truth heere amongſt vs, we haue profeſſed, but wee haue not pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed it as we ſhould,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:6766:85"/>yet becauſe it is the planting of thine own right hand: ſuffer not our ſinnes to pluck vp the ſame: but rather ſupplant our ſinnes and thereby ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then our ſtates and ſoules: To this end (good and gracious God) looke vpon thy ſeruant our Soueraign whom thou haſt ſet ouer vs: inlighten his royall heart with thy ſauing Graces of knowledg, piety, cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, care, prouidence, for preſeruation and aduancement of thy
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:6766:86"/>truth, and of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that thou haſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his charge. Giue him Zeale, forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, power, peace and protection againſt all that are Enemies to true Religion, and to thoſe Realmes thou haſt appointed him to rule: Giue him a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning heart to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer and ſhun all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and all that bee dangerous to him and to his Dominions, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite his heart in loue to his people, and them in loyalty to him. O LORD,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:6766:86"/>preſerue thy people vnder him in peace: Protect them from forrayne power, and both him and them from home-bred con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies, and all other miſchieuous machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations: Make the Prince, his Magiſtrates and People zealous of thy ſeruice and glory, conſtant and carefull in keeping thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements: coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious for defence of thy Trueth, and their Countrey: Conſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and Charitable. That ſo they may bee
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:6766:87"/>ſtill thy faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants and thou their mercifull God: So ſhall thy glorious Goſpell and the light of thy Trueth euer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine amongſt vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the comming of thy Sonne Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus: that thou mayeſt raigne ouer vs: and we remaine with thee in eternall Bliſſe. <hi>Amen. Amen.</hi> Good Lord.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="149" facs="tcp:6766:87"/>
            <head>A Prayer for our afflicted Brethren, the Proteſtants be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas:</head>
            <p>MOſt gracious and merciful Father, who vſeſt to chaſten thy Children, and to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect whom thou lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, Haue mercy on thoſe that ſuffer for mainetenance of thy trueth: Their ſinnes
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:6766:88"/>haue deſerued thy pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, and yet we that haue ſinned as much, if not more, haue not ſuffered ſo much for our ſinnes: Thou haſt ſent thy ſcourge to let them ſee their ſinnes. Thou haſt not gone out with their hoſtes, but haſt ſcattered them. O Lord yet heale and binde vp their bones which thou haſt bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: gather them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and now thou haſt taught the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that their power is in vaine without thy
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:6766:88"/>protection, and the people that there is no confidence in the arme of fleſh, giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yet confidence in thy fauour, patience in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity, courage to fight for thy Trueth, comfort amidſt their calamities: O Lord thou doeſt permit thy people Iſrael many times after thy long ſufferings, and their great ſinnes to bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome by the <hi>Iebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites, Amalachites</hi> and <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> The <hi>Arke</hi> was taken, and they cried out, the glory of
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:6766:89"/>Iſrael was departed, yet thou didſt ſend helpe, when there was no helpe nor hope in Man: O Lord thou haſt executed Iuſtice and Iudgement, yet leaue not thine to their oppreſſors, and when thou haſt dealt with them according to thy mercy, teach them thy Statutes; that they may know thy Teſtimonies. It is time (O Lord) for thee to worke, for the perſecutors of the Trueth haue deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy Law: The
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:6766:89"/>Kings of the earth band themſelues, and the Princes are aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled together againſt the Lord and his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed. O yet thou Lord of Hoſtes breake their bandes in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and caſt away their cordes: And though the waters rage and be troubled, yet let thy ſeruants finde and ſay; the Lord of hoſtes is with them, and the God of <hi>Iacob</hi> is their refuge. And that when thy ſeruants, our perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted brethren, haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:6766:90"/>comfort and deliuerance; they may reioyce in thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, ſing praiſes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, and call vnto their neighbors, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the wonderfull workes thou haſt done for them, to make it knowen vnto the world. It is thou that makeſt wars to ceaſe: It is thou that haſt broken the bowe, cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt the ſpeare, and burneſt the Chatiot in ſunder: So we pray for them and for one another: Beſeeching thee to graunt vs theſe
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:6766:90"/>requeſts. For thy Sonnes ſake our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="156" facs="tcp:6766:91"/>
            <head>A Prayer to bee vſed on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath Day.</head>
            <p>O Lord God of infinite pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, who after thy euer to bee admired and praiſed worke of creating this World, didſt ordaine one day of ſeauen to bee kept as a Sabboth; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be free from la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:6766:91"/>and trauell, but to be wholly dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and kept holy, for thy ſeruice in Prayers and praiſes, to be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto thy Maieſtie, as an incenſe and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of thankefull acknowledgement of thy moſt great might and mercies; in crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this world and ordayning man to gouerne all creatures therein conteyned: in conſeruing all theſe thy Creatures for his vſe, and him for thy ſeruice, in giuing him light of Knowledge
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:6766:92"/>and vnderſtanding, of thy Word and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement: and of the things hee ſhould doe, or leaue vndone. As we receiue theſe thy bleſſings and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, ſo ſpecially on this day, which thou haſt ſelected for thy ſeruice. O Lord ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle vs vnto it, fit vs for it, and grant grace not only vnto vs heere preſent, but to the publicke ſtate, and to particular perſons in other places: not only to reſt from la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours on this day, but
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:6766:92"/>to ſhun ſinne, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants in thy ſeruice, to read thy Word, to heare it, where it is preached; to come vnto thy Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and where thy word is not preached, to vſe all the good meanes wee may for maintenance and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of knowledge and of conſcience; by praying, reading, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating and confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. To this end (good Lord) teach vs to caſt away, as all ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile workes, ſo ſloth,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:6766:93"/>euill and idle compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny-keeping, prophane ſpeeches, with other euill actions and thoughts; that may either draw vs from our Chriſtian dueties, offend thy diuine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, or giue euill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample vnto others: Make our hearts and Conſciences cleane, our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferences, words and workes holy, and conuerſation vpright and pure. So begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and continuing in thy ſeruice this day in ſuch ſort as thou requireſt, wee may
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:6766:93"/>not onely ſanctifie this, but all the reſt of thy Sabbaths, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the remayne of our dayes heere vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth: vntill wee come to that Sabbath of Sabbaths, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall reſt: reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and prayſing of thy Holy and Bleſſed Name in the higheſt Heauens: wherein grant vs the aſſiſtance of thy holy Spirit, and the aide of thy Sonne our Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="160" facs="tcp:6766:94"/>
            <head>A Prayer in the time of trouble and affliction.</head>
            <p>O LORD our God: great are our ſins, and heauie are our vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitations: yet our cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſments are nothing anſwerable to our corruption, wee haue ſinned much and thou haſt ſuffered vs long, yet though our ſinnes
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:6766:94"/>be as redde as ſcarlet, thou haſt ſaid and we beleeue that thou wilt make them as white as ſnow. Our ſinnes do feſter through our owne Corruptions, cleanſe them, (O thou the ſoueraigne &amp; ſole phiſitian of our ſoules: Since thou art pleaſed to purge vs with ſome bitter pills that vrge vs to ſweat and groane yet more for world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly matters then for the offence of thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Maieſtie. Make vs therefore firſt ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of our ſinnes and
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:6766:95"/>ſorowfull for them: And when thou haſt purged vs, take away thy puniſhments: Cure firſt our ſoules, then make our bodies and eſtates ſound and ſafe: Yet againe and againe bring vs backe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider and ſee from whence all our cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities doe come, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vs (if it bee thy bleſſed will from pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and enſuing dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, or elſe graunt vs patience to vndergoe whatſoeuer thy good pleaſure ſhalbe to lay vpon vs: Renew vs
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:6766:95"/>and then reſtore vs to thy wonted fauour, not for our merits but for the merites and mercies of thy beloued Sonne, and our bleſſed Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="164" facs="tcp:6766:96"/>
            <head>A Prayer when publique Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities approach or are doubted.</head>
            <p>OOr ſinnes (O Lord) haue drawne vpon vs thy heauy diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and greater pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments then yet we feele or feare, for wee haue multiplied our offences, and yet thou haſt held backe thy
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:6766:96"/>puniſhing hand, wee haue not been allured by thy merits though they be many, nor ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed by thy cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſent to draw vs vnto conformity: But rather thy long ſuffering hath made vs more ſecure, hard hearted and negligent: This hath cauſed thee ſometimes to ſend ſignes of thy fearefull wrath, as ſickeneſſe, vnſeaſonable weather, want of meanes to maintaine many who heretofore haue liued well: Our brethren
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:6766:97"/>abroad profeſſing the ſame Religion ſuffer many heauy preſſuers and are in much perill, wee at home though we haue long enioyed the liberty of exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Religion wee profeſſe, yet our cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and careleſſenes in practiſing (beſides our many other ſins) hath hindered the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of piety, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonored thy name, and indangered the truth: O Lord, yet at length, humble vs in the ſight and ſenſe of theſe our ſins: Teach
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:6766:97"/>vs to learne, conſider and remember, that for ſuch, if not for leſſe ſinnes, thou didſt conſume Sodom, draw the deluge ouer the whole earth, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, almoſt conſume at an inſtant all the Creatures of the World.</p>
            <p>Yet neither theſe examples nor our own chaſtiſements haue preuailed to perſwade vs vnto true humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, repentance and amendment of life: But now of late when thou haſt ſent ſignes
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:6766:98"/>in the ayre, inundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of waters, peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, pouerty, decay of trades: and haſt found amongſt vs a decreaſe of deſire to doe good: a deſire to deceiue, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ide of hart, delicious and luxuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous liuing, periury, and perfidious dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, profanation of thy Name, Word and Sacraments: So that there being little hope of better beliefe, or of better liuing when thy ſword of Iuſtice is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be drawne, the light of trueth in ſome
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:6766:98"/>danger to be dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; and wee to receiue ſuch puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as we moſt iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue deſerued: Yet conſider wee are the workemanſhip ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for thy ſeruice: And though the Axe ſhould be put vnto the tree, ready to out of our liues, eſtates and ſauing knowledge, yet correct, but doe not (for thy mercies ſake) confound vs; reforme but do not deſtroy vs: Make vs yet new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: O ſpare and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iuer vs from the euill
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:6766:99"/>daies to come: Thou deſireſt not the death of ſinners, but rather Conuerſion, Let vs yet liue to honor thee whom we haue diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed; Though long peace and much plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hath ſet vs a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eepe, and prouoked vs to much pride and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, yet let vs with <hi>Hezechiah,</hi> tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the wall and weeping, be repriued from that ſentence which our ſinnes haue ſent out againſt vs: and let vs learne to ſerue thee and not Sathan:
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:6766:99"/>So being preſerued by thy mercy wee may yeeld Honour and praiſe to thy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="174" facs="tcp:6766:100"/>
            <head>A Prayer againſt the raigning ſins that a man findes to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maine in himſelfe.</head>
            <p>LOrd God, how ſenſeleſſe am I of mine owne ſinnes, that cannot ſee nor feele thoſe I daily and continually com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit: Some are ſecret and concealed from my ſelf which I know not or cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue.
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:6766:100"/>And thoſe though leſſe haynous, or at the leaſt, leſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, yet too hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy for me to beare, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther greater and more grieuous by mee not acknowledged, or not repented: and amongſt many more that I paſſe ouer without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny examination of my ſelfe or repentance for them: Thoſe cleaue moſt to the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of mine owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as pride, ſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, and other ſinnes whereto I am moſt ſubiect, &amp;c. Theſe
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:6766:101"/>preſſe mee moſt, and others too much; yet pardon mee (O Lord) pardon that is paſt, purge me from them for time to come, cleanſe the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of my nature, cure the Contagion that comes by euill company and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticements of others, with whoſe faſhions, wits, faces or flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, wee are ſeduced: And for mine owne inward concupiſcenſe which eaſily ſets it ſelfe on fire: O Lord quench it with the
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:6766:101"/>cooling and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting giftes of Grace, ſobrietie, temperance and circumſpection. Bee thou (moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious God) that good <hi>Samaritan,</hi> to poure into my wounded ſoule the oyle of thy mercy, that ſo theſe deſtroyers of my ſoule being by thee deſtroyed, I may then ſurely ſay, <hi>O Death</hi> where is thy ſting: <hi>O Hell</hi> where is thy victory, and bleſſe thee, who haſt bleſſed mee with thine abundant mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies:
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:6766:102"/>to whom bee praiſes and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for euer <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="179" facs="tcp:6766:102"/>
            <head>A Prayer neceſſary to be vſed often</head>
            <p>O LORD God moſt mighty mercifull and iuſt, who haſt created all things of nothing only by thy power and word, who haſt preſerued all that thou haſt made, and doeſt ſaue all thoſe that doe faithfully call and truſt on thee. Wee
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:6766:103"/>moſt miſerable and wretched ſinners doe confeſſe vnto thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our ſelues to our owne ſhame and to thy glory, that wee were borne and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in ſinne, that wee haue liued and continued in ſinne: that our whole liues haue beene nothing elſe but a heaping vp of ſinne and iniquity againſt thy Holy and Heauenly Maieſtie: That there is no ſinne in his owne nature ſo heynous, or to thee ſo diſpleaſing but either
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:6766:103"/>wee haue committed or elſe wee haue a proneneſſe to commit the ſame. The ſinnes of our youth; of our riper age and of our later, euen of theſe laſt time shaue flowed one vpon another, and haue polluted our ſoules, defiled our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and diſpleaſed thy Maieſtie, ſo that there is nothing due vnto vs, if thou ſhouldſt deale with vs according to our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, but death and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction in this life, Hell and perdition in
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:6766:104"/>the life to come. Whither then ſhould we flie for ſuccour and reliefe: If we goe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Man, his breath is in his noſtrils: that periſhing he periſheth: If wee goe vnto An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, or to any power in Heauen, they haue no power but what they receiue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from thee; We come there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vnto thee, whoſe mercy is aboue all thy workes, beſeeching thee in the multitude of thy mercies to haue compaſſion on vs. And in that loue
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:6766:104"/>(which thou ſhewedſt vnto Mankind, in ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thy Son to ſuffer for vs, and to ſaue vs ſinners, that thou wouldſt by his blood, death and ſuffering, waſh away our ſinnes: And ſince thou haſt ſent him to Redeeme vs, ſuffer vs not to be deſtroyed: O Lord GOD, graunt vs penitence and true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance for our ſins paſt, watchfulneſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all our wayes for time to come, Care to keepe thy Comman dements, ſtrength to
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:6766:105"/>withſtand the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Satan. Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of heart, patience in the times of tryall and aduerſitie: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy in calling vpon thee: Feruency in prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Faith in thy promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Aſſurance of thy loue: Aſſiſtance in Temptations, Deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from dangers of ſoule and body, The right and Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied vſe of thy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: Charitie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our neighbors: and contentednes with our eſtates, To this end (gracious God)
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:6766:105"/>take from vs all thoſe things that take vs from thee, and giue vs thoſe graces that may make vs to loue thee, and declare vs to be intirely beloued of thee. Take from vs hardneſſe of heart, dulneſſe and ſlownes, in comming to thy ſeruice, Neglect of thoſe Holy duties thou requireſt vs to doe: Contempt of thy Commaundements, Miſbeliefe, Vnbeliefe, Deſpaire and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thy mercy: Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt of thy proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:6766:106"/>Giue vs, aboue all things, Faith, ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ly to beleeue in thee, feruour in thy ſeruice: faithfulneſſe in maintenance of thy trueth: courage to lay downe our liues for the continuance of thy glorious Goſpell: thankefulneſſe for all thy vnſpeakable mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies: a loue of thoſe that ſerue thee in ſin cerity of heart, Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie (according to our abilities) to thoſe that are in diſtreſſe and danger for doing that they ought to do.
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:6766:106"/>And when thou haſt fitted vs for thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and furniſhed our hearts with thy good graces, then ſend vs the ioy of thy Holy Spirit, a deteſtation of our former euill cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, delight in keeping thy Lawes, a deſire to bee diſſolued in thy good appointed time, a meditation of our fraile liues, and a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine deaths: And now (O bleſſed Lord) wee pray not for our ſelues alone here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but for thy deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:6766:107"/>diſperſed and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed flocke throgh the face of the earth: It is a little flocke. O Lord increaſe it: It is diſperſed, O Lord ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> together into thy fold: It is deſpiſed &amp; diſtreſſed. Lord ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour defend &amp; ſupport them: Let not the wild Boares deſtroy thy Vineyard; nor the fat Bulles of Baſan inuiro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ouerwhelme thy choſen ones, &amp; thoſe that loue thy trueth: Thou haſt heretofore hedged thy Syon, Thou haſt mightily
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:6766:107"/>and miraculouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended thy choſen Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael: Thy hand is not ſhortned thy power is ſtill the ſame: Let not therefore thoſe that loue not thy trueth, or them that loue it, ſay; where is now their God. Be mercifull to our ſoueraign, &amp; to all the Royall Progeny: Gouerne the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of this Land, Giue them true wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſincere, vncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, and couragious hearts: Innoble the true Nobility, with Loyaltie to their
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:6766:108"/>Prince and State, the leading of a good life, and the longing for a better. Inſpire the Clergie, with care and diligence to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge their duties in their ſeuerall places: Make the Commons of this Kingdome more iuſt, more holy, more conſcionable in their courſes, more carefull of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſafety and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of the publike State: touch vs all with a zeale of thy feruice and truth, an inward reuerence of
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:6766:108"/>thy moſt holy Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, a remorſe of our former irreligious life That ſo when wee ſhall part from this place, wee may part from our ſinnes, but not from ſorrow for hauing committed them; but may leaue them and leade a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter life, till wee bee brought from death to that life where ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and ſin raigneth not, where death hath no dominion, and where complaints &amp; controuerſies are not known, but haue their
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:6766:109"/>ende. This life, good Lord, graunt vs to leade in thy feare, and in the ende, to inioy that life, where ioyes doe laſt for euer, by the mercies of thee our Lord and onely Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="193" facs="tcp:6766:109"/>
            <head>A Prayer againſt Pride anger and Enuy.</head>
            <p>O LORD God who ſeeſt and ſearcheſt the ſecrets of all mens hearts; Thou that knoweſt how ſubiect I am to Pride, Anger and Enuie: My heart (good Lord) is puffed vp with pride, it ſweſs with ſelfe conceipt,
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:6766:110"/>vaine glory and oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: I take too much pride of thoſe parts of my Bodie, as beautie, ſtrength and ſtature, and make my ſelfe beleeue they are much more faire and faſhionable then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede they are. So am I efflated and blowne vp like a bladder with conceit of mine owne knowledg, wit, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and skill, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them greater and more goodly vnto my ſelfe then they are or can bee; Theſe foule faults (gracious God)
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:6766:110"/>ſometimes I finde in my ſelfe, but nothing ſo often as I commit them: And though now I confeſſe it, yet I haue no power of my ſelfe to forſake this ſinne, by which our firſt Parents fell out of Paradiſe, and we his ſinnefull Progeny fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the ſame ſteppes, and are ready thereby to runne headlong vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Hell. O yet (moſt merciful father) clenſe me from this corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, cure me and I ſhal be cleane, graunt me a lowly, penitent and
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:6766:111"/>humble heart: Teach me to thinke worſe of my ſelfe for my ſins then of other men whoſe faults I know not; that I may not thinke ſo well of my ſelfe to contemne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: O teach me to learne meckeneſſe of thee my Sauiour, who in thy humanitie haſt ledde vs to the way of humblenes and meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe both of thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and practiſe: Thou haſt ſaid, learne of me for I am meeke, O ſweet Sauiour, what precept could bee
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:6766:111"/>ſweeter, better or what Example could bee more Holy and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. If <hi>Lucifer</hi> an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of Heauen could not bee ſafe but was caſt downe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence through pride and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancy: How ſhould I bee ſafe whileſt I commit this ſinne ſo much, and ſo often heere on earth: Purge me therefore O God from Pride, and leade me by thy Heauenly hand vnto Humility, and lowlines of heart: Lord God how much am I ouerwhelmed
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:6766:112"/>with wrath and anger, how ſuddainly incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, vpon how ſmall and ſlender occaſions am I moued by wrath to vſe reproach, and to ſeeke reuenge, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake Charity, to ſeeke others harme, and to aduenture mine owne ruine; ſo that my minde cannot be pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable and quiet: So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainely by anger, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is diſturbed, loue and good will forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, Faith broken, and fury drawing mee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to madneſſe, by which I breake the
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:6766:112"/>bounds of Chriſtian Charitie, I beſeech thee (good Lord) (who feeſt how much I am ſubiect to this finne) make me more patient and peaceable, ſuppreſſe this paſſion of anger in me, that I may paſſe by ſmall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences and may not bee ſodainely prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vnto impatience: O Lord infuſe into me moderation and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie, temperance and ſobriety, by which, and eſpecially by the aſſiſtance of thy holy Spirit, I may bee able
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:6766:113"/>to maſter anger and paſſion, the furies of my minde, and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of my Soule, And if anger at any time ſeize on mee, graunt that it may be ſetled on the zeale of thy truth, and the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of thee my God, for the ſuppreſſing of ſuperſtition, and the ſeeking to vindicate thine honour againſt ſuch as ſeeke to diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thee by Atheiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, profaneneſſe and impiety, yet ſo as I ſin not by raſhneſſe or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiling, but by making
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:6766:113"/>a difference betwixt the perſons and their peruerſenes, reſeruing Charitie to the one, and labouring refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the other: take from me O Lord God, enuy and malice, ſuffer me not to fret at the proſperity of any, no not of the wicked and impious perſons whoſe bounds are ſet, beyond which they ſhall not bee able to goe, much leſſe let me enuy them who walke in vpright waies. But if through offence or iniuries I haue been at
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:6766:114"/>any time prouoked to proceede againſt them yet let mee not conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue with them in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention through diſlike or diſguſt to wiſh them euill: But teach me by ſingleneſſe and ſincerity of heart to ſhunne the malicing of any man; that ſo ſhewing mercy and meekeneſſe I may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue mercy from thee that art the Lord of mercy: to whom bee giuen Honour and glory now and for euer <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="203" facs="tcp:6766:114"/>
            <head>A Prayer of Thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing after deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from Sickeneſſe and Danger of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe.</head>
            <p>THou O Lord moſt mighty and mercifull haſt ſent ſickeneſſe as a ſcourge for ſinne, as a tryall of our Faith, and teſtimony of thy fauour, when it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thee to reſtore
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:6766:115"/>health. Thou haſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited me and brought me neere the gates of Death, yet haſt thou deliuered mee from danger, to the end I might publiſh thy praiſe and lead a more godly life, Feare came vpon mee on euery ſide, my fleſh &amp; Spirit did faint, but thy holy hand did ſuſtaine mee and helpe mee vp: What praiſes (moſt gracious God) ſhall I render vnto thee for thy protection and preſeruation: But that I doe as I am able.
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:6766:115"/>And, O Lord, inable me more to laude thee, more to call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy name, and to ſhew thy workes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the people, to ſing vnto thee prayſes for this thy mercy in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuering me from the danger of Death; And now that thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored mee to health, O Lord, reſtore mee to thy fauour: And as thou haſt giuen ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth vnto my body: ſo bleſſed God, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then my Soule againſt Sinne and Satan, that I may liue to giue thee
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:6766:116"/>Glory; and during this fading life, I may bee made faithfull in keeping thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, ſeruing thee in ſinceritie of ſoule: and ſeeking thy glory both now, and at all times, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="207" facs="tcp:6766:116"/>
            <head>A Prayer for the mainetenance of Peace.</head>
            <p>O LORD God moſt mighty and gracious: Our ſinnes are great and grieuous, our pride, malice and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, begets conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whence growes Warres and Deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Blood-ſhedding and deſtruction: thou
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:6766:117"/>that art the Lord of Hoſtes, ſeeſt it is in the hands of Princes to make warres, but it is in thy power only to end them, and to ſaue thy people: Great are the gatherings and forces already of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med men, ready to deſtroy one another, and great is like to be the ſlaughter, Except thou moſt mercifull God, be pleaſed to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie the minds of the Princes, and of the People, and to ſaue them who otherwiſe will fall to ſlaughter.
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:6766:117"/>Take yet (moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God) thine owne Cauſe into thine own hand, help thy people that profeſſethy truth, leſt they periſh: Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue them from pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rills: Saue, good Lord, ſuch as ſerue thee in truth, and call vpon thee in ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of heart: Let not the Mightie ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelme thy choſen Children, but either let the Oppreſſors feele thy power, or make them to incline their heartes vnto peace, and ſo ſaue the
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:6766:118"/>effuſion of bloud, and temper the hearts of Chriſtian Princes that they may come to the Knowledge of the truth, that Mercy and Truth may meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, that righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and peace may kiſſe each other. So bee it, good Lord.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb n="207" facs="tcp:6766:118"/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Aug: Mathewes</hi> for <hi>Robert Swayne,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his Shop at the Signe of the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Britaines Burſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6766:119" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6766:119"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
